[SPEAKER_01]: So, in regards to meditation on kindness, metta meditation, you said in the past, and I'll just, I'll just read you what you said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Metta meditation is the surmounting of your mind from delighting in
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: What I meant was, you don't want to be doing or fabricating kindness artificially.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you can do that as a form of management, as we spoke before.
[SPEAKER_00]: If your mind is gripped by a will...
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not the loving-kindness meditation, because if that's done rightly, that's on the level of jhānas, and it can certainly result in the mind development to the level of becoming an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Brahma-viharas, if they're done properly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not just your casual, beaming, radiant, happy thoughts, and things like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's really seeing the basis of your real will, experiencing complete equanimity,
[SPEAKER_00]: When I say basis, I mean that ill-will is bound with, it's inseparable from, it's determined by.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're indifferent towards the determination of the ill-will, you cannot possibly be experiencing that ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then also, you have no choice but to be free from ill-will towards people.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the basis of ill-will, it's others.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just... Again, you might have ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: By the time ill-will manifests, it's usually aimed at somebody.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the basis of it is just the factual presence of others in that general sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others different than me, different than this point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you start experiencing equanimity on that level, then there is no ill-will that can develop further down the line.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in practical terms, you just have to see that
[SPEAKER_00]: No matter how justified your ill-will might be towards somebody, a person, that ill-will and that notion of personality is inseparated, inseparable from the physical aspect of their body, of their body, of my body, of our bodies.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that physical aspect is subject to basically to sickness, aging, death.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's truly not in your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, you realize that even any ill-will that has intentionally been inflicted upon you from others, it was done circumstantially so, because they themselves are not fundamentally the owners of their body.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the sense, they do own it as a mistake, as a putujana, sort of appropriates things around it, but once you realize that you can't own, nobody can own their bodies.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everybody is subject to the same universal principles of anicca and things not being in your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, things that you do experience on account of intentions of others, you can't take in that ultimate sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will then produce your ill-will in return.
[SPEAKER_00]: You would see it basically as circumstantial, like beings acting out of ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I don't mean that in a patronizing sense, like, forgive them, they're ignorant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just factual.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know that when there is ill-will in you, it's because
[SPEAKER_00]: You've taken your body to be permanent, to be in control, and now you're expressing the ill-will, or lust, for that matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you see it in others, you see the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by understanding it in yourself, you'll understand it in others.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, it just... it becomes impossible for ill-will to arise, for as long as you don't ignore that fact, that they are not in control, their own five aggregates, the way they present themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if they were, they would be, like, truly,
[SPEAKER_00]: Masked, they wouldn't be subject to any impermanence, any sickness, any death, nothing like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they are.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they're not.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when they act like they're gonna last forever, you just see clearly that's out of the same delusion that you would be acting out, if you're making the same mistake.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why, if you were to understand that, you basically understand the whole nature of anicca.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you were to genuinely practice metta meditation, like impossibility of ill-will,
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, yeah, you want...
[SPEAKER_00]: Automatically, what you're gonna feel towards them is compassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not a sort of smarmy, tree-hugging sort of type of compassion just to all of the radiant beings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just indulging, basically, self-indulging.
[SPEAKER_00]: But more of a genuine compassion of... Oh, yeah, there's a genuine ignorance there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if they would only know better, they wouldn't have not done that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you know that for a fact, because nobody actually wants to be acting out of ignorance, unless they're already ignorant.
[SPEAKER_01]: What about you just have ill-will?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, if the ill-will is present, you just... first step is you must not act out of it, by body, by speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, eventually, you should stop acting out of, like, even in your mind, in terms of having the unwholesome thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just something that's a new, like, arising of those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Possibility of acting by body, possibility of acting by speech,
[SPEAKER_00]: Even possibility of acting by mind, they're not on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those things present themselves as possibility of the presently arisen experience of ill-will, but you are the one intentionally delighting in it, entertaining it, and then proliferating it further.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's on you, and that's what you don't want to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you stop doing that, then you'll be perfectly capable of enduring the arisen ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you would know mind affected by ill-will as mind affected by ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's... that's all it would be.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can already, by seeing it in that manner, you already start recognizing that you can't own it, even if you want to.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when you, when you fully cannot, when you fully sort of discern that, then there won't be any ill-will anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ill-will, it's when basically a disagreeable experience in regard to others is appropriated as mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's an automatic ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes he instructs people,
[SPEAKER_00]: He spends lots of time instructing them, but then they go and do the opposite, despite all the efforts that he put into teaching them.
[SPEAKER_00]: But because of that, the target's mind doesn't experience any ill-will or unwholesome thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: He experiences a disagreeable feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, oh, look at this foolish man.
[SPEAKER_00]: I've been wasting my time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he doesn't regard everything as pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he said that disagreeable feeling cannot persist and overwhelm the mind of the Tathāgata and basically turn it into a will aimed at that person.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what about thinking about, you know, kind thoughts beforehand, before... you're not... you don't have ill-will, but you... Well, if you're thinking about kind thoughts, you're most likely going to be thinking on the level of other people as other selves, which means you're just revolving around the problem of taking things as mine, which means sooner or later ill-will will replace that kindness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, your fabrication and management, I mean, it's only relatively effective, in a sense of just kind of
[SPEAKER_00]: Pushing it away for a bit longer and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, you need to recognize that you should not be dwelling in entertaining your will and sort of giving rise to it when you can, and certainly acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But thinking that you can just replace it with thoughts of kindness, just focus on this experience as opposed to that experience, that's all it does.
[SPEAKER_00]: It replaces one experience with the other experience, but doesn't bring the understanding of the nature of experience all in itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot bring that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're just concerned with the content of that experience and just replacing one with the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you don't know that you're supposed to see beyond the content of the experience into the nature of experience, the universal principles, which is what dhamma is, then you'll never... you will never look there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because... because you need to... you need to basically be told and then recognize that and then start making effort of seeing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It won't be shown by itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't stumble upon dhamma accidentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, think kind thoughts,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still better... thinking kind thoughts is still better than thinking unwholesome thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: But don't mistake that as a way of out of both wholesome and unwholesome thoughts, which is what you want to achieve.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's what metta does.
[SPEAKER_00]: Metta is basically absence of your will.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean love.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's just a completely different experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's absence of love as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why if you do brahma-vihāras correctly, the highest of them is the equanimity, upeka, complete indifference, imperturbable.